All right, this is a short research
update August 8th, 2025 about using
generalized coordinates of motion models
of various orders in RX infer to take
noisy samples and do path inference on
the underlying smooth trajectory and
then compare how the different orders,
so different moments of the
distribution, how well they do in terms
of confidence interval coverage. free
energy minimization etc across different
scenarios. So this is all in the rx
infer examples.jl repo on my personal
doxology fork. If you want to learn more
about generalized coordinates start with
the Wikipedia or the paper basian
mechanics for stationary processes which
is live stream 26.
So here we have some numbers of orders
of generalized coordinates
and what is happening in this repository
is that in the research generalized
coordinates and order there's a model
visualization folder. This is going to
make visualizations
of each of the model orders. So this is
like a low order first order one and
this is a sixth order and they're all
put together in this collage
that has all of the orders. Here it's 1
through eight but there's a app model
block generator so that you can use any
order you want. The outputs folder has
one general case and then it separates
into different orders. So we'll look at
the uh third order generalized
coordinates of motion model and there's
a scenario generator that generates
three different
uh cases and each each situation for
each order is going to get all these
outputs. So first is the position uh
position, velocity, acceleration,
however many orders are being
considered. What fraction of the time is
the inference within the 95%
confidence interval actually including
the true value?
Here's the dashboard. Here's the
position, velocity, acceleration, and
the free energy through time. the true
and the inferred value here because it
was essentially uh a smooth moving
scenario. The third order approximation
did really well. But if we look at that
constant scenario
with a first order approximation
basically it just is a straight line.
And if we look at the sign
scenario here again the first order
approximation all it can do is basically
draw the best straight line through this
whole data set. Whereas if we go to the
sign
with a third order approximation we're
getting
uh the ability to latch on to capture
the position velocity acceleration. So
coverage within the confidence interval
dashboard,
some information on the derivatives,
the error profile, cumulative sum and
free energy through time. Some of the
artifacts at the very beginning and the
very end are just relative to the the it
being earlier late data points.
uh
mean squared error through time for each
of those position, velocity, and
acceleration.
Uh histogram of the residuals,
root mean squared for each of those
states. Here, a scatter plot, the
position, velocity, acceleration. So, it
latched on pretty well. Again, if we
look at the first order,
true versus inferred
here, all all it can do is just guess on
this straight line
uh a QQ plot. So, definitely leaves some
room to be improved quantitatively, but
just structurally was what I was seeking
to get here. uh residuals through time,
overall fit to the noisy data. Again,
the goal was to go from noisy
observations to the predictions of the
underlying data, some metrics, uh
written report
and information on the scenario
that is happening
uh for each scenario that gets
metaanalyzed across the scenarios. So
here we have
the mean correlation
for these three scenarios the the
constant the peace-wise mixed and the
sign only. So let's just look at what
the peacewise mixed looks like.
This one
has every 500 time steps it kind of
switches into a different regime.
So that really challenges the
approximation
and we can see that
for example on the constant situation
the all the orders do really well
because it's pretty easy in the
peace-wise and in the sign situation the
low orders do bad and the higher orders
do fine and there's diminishing returns
once you get into these higher
derivatives.
Here's another way to look at this. This
is the the 95% confidence interval
showing how again in the two more
complex situations the
uh low order models are not able to work
that well. But then increasingly high
order models do better and better
and similar patterns are observed for
free energy values.
Again, realistically at at super high
orders, you're getting weird overfitting
errors.
And that is all happening from the uh
the situation is is the car situation.
It's just imagining that there's a car.
It was based off of the hierarchical
Gaussian filter.
So here's the uh example that was uh
based off of which was basically this
hierarchical Gaussian
filter situation.
And
in the generalized coordinates, it's
configured
through uh the ability to to
uh run the suite
across uh different orders.
And
in SRC
is where the model is.
So here's the basis of the RX infer
model and here's the constraint block
that is used to generate all those
combinations.
So again, generalized coordinates. This
uh folder,
this one is just three orders.
This one's just uh uh three
different uh
orders of of motion.
And then I generalized that into the n
orders of generalized coordinates in
that folder. hgf is if you want to look
more at how the hierarchical gaussian
filter works
and all that is based upon these rx
infer examples. And also while you're
here check out the visualization
methods folder also in research. This is
a generalized way to look at all the
different RX infer models. So whether
it's the the coin toss or it's the drone
model
or this generalized coordinates model
the the base form or it's a hidden marov
model. These are some visualization
methods. So, hope that is useful and
interesting for those who like
open-source statistical methods, RX and
for learning about generalized
coordinates, free energy principle,
pathbased formulations, rough paths, all
the good stuff. So, thanks for watching.
Bye.